Finding aid to the Ruth Mehrtens Galvin papers SSC.MS.00181
Sophia Smith Collection
Ruth Mehrtens Galvin papers
1858-2002
Sophia Smith Collection
Galvin, Ruth Mehrtens, 1922-2002
SSC.MS.00181
24 boxes (29 linear feet)
The papers contain the records of Ruth Mehrtens Galvin, journalis and editor. Papers consist of research files, notebooks, writings (published and unpublished), pocket diaries, correspondence for her Time magazine work, lectures, and memorabilia. Writings and research cover topics with an emphasis on women's issues, as well as aging, race, drugs, psychology, and sexuality. Includes material on the National Women's Conference in Houston, 1977, which Galvin covered for Time, and interviews with Gloria Steinem, Helvi Siipola and Donna Leirhoff.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. Collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use. Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by Ruth Mehrtens Galvin in 1985 (85S-44), 1986 (86S-1), 1990 (90S-73), 1991 (91S-7), 1999, and 2003.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth Beatrice Mehrtens Galvin was born New Haven, 14 Jan 1922, daughter of Behrend and Paulin Clara (Gademann) Mehrtens. She received her A.B. from Smith College in 1942. She was a letters correspondent for Life magazine, 1945-46; then became a researcher, then contributing editor for Time magazine in 1946. From 1951 on, she was a correspondent for Time in Chicago, Canada, London, Boston, and Israel; bureau chief in Boston 1960-66; a national correspondent, 1966-74; and senior correspondent from 1974 until her retirement in 1985. She also worked as a freelance journalist; was a member of the Smith Alumnae Quarterly editorial board, 1968-71; and was a Smith College Trustee, 1987-88, and 1991-92. She married Roderick Allen McManigal, 1947; divorced; married John Thomas Galvin, 1968. Ruth Galvin died 23 Oct 2002.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Related Material
Associated material located in Smith College Archives.
Scope and Contents
The Ruth Mehrtens Galvin Papers consist of research files, notebooks, writings (published and unpublished), pocket diaries, correspondence for her Time magazine work, lectures, and memorabilia. Her writings and research files cover a wide range of topics with an emphasis on women's issues, including aging, alcoholism, blacks, divorce, drugs, the Equal rights Amendment, homosexuality, Matina Horner, Masters and Johnson, Edward Kennedy, mental health/illness, pornography, psychology, rape, sexuality, Smith College, violence, and widows. There is substantial material collected from the National Women's Conference in Houston, 1977, which Galvin covered for Time. The collection also includes taped interviews of prominent women including Gloria Steinem, Helvi Siipola and Donna Leirhoff.
Journalism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Journalists--United States--20th century--Biography--Sources; Women journalists--United States--20th century--Biography--Sources; Women editors--United States--Biography--Sources; Women's rights--United States--History--20th century--Sources; correspondence; Writings; Speeches; Oral histories; Interviews; Manuscripts; diaries; scrapbooks; Audiotapes; photographs; notebooks; clippings; Galvin, Ruth Mehrtens, 1922-; National Women's Conference (1st: 1977: Houston, Tex.) Time, inc.; Galvin, Ruth Mehrtens; Galvin, Ruth Mehrtens
- Ruth Mehrtens Galvin: biographical, genealogical materials, 1858-2002; 2003-S-0046; 3 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Woodburn, Jr., R. Robert
  - Books: Smith Voices: Selected works by Smith College Women, 1990; Smith Women: Selected Works by Smith College Alumnae, 1999, 1990-1999; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - American Psychiatric Association plaque, 1999; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Magazines with articles pertaining to Galvin, 1963-1997; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Wedding album including related, unrelated correspondence, clippings, 1947-1950; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 2000, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1933-1939; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1947-1956; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Blank postcards from European travel, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - European trip maps, brochures, 1949; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1917, 1949, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Education: report cards, aptitude assessments, scholarship applications, and Smith College memorabilia, 1928-1942; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Frederick Gatterman's application for U.S. citizenship, 1858; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Essay, typescript, possibly by Galvin, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Essay notes, possibly by Galvin, 2002 April 30; 2003-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, clippings, other biographical and genealogical materials, 1922-2001; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, writings and clippings, 1973-1995; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Wedding and family photographs, 1967-1976, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject files: Ray Flynn, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: Senda Berenson, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: Julia Child, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: Cardinal Cushing, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: shyness, undated; 2003-46-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: Hal Tinker, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject files: Pilot Medal, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: Smith College Archives, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: op-ed, jury duty, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: New York Times, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: Henry Hough, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Subject file: David McCord, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1952-1953; 2003-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Junior high school diploma, 1935; 2003-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - High school diploma, 1938; 2003-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Galvin's parents' marriage certificate, 1917; 2003-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - School class photographs, 1932; 1937; 2003-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - National Gallery of Arty reproduction prints, undated; 2003-S-0046 (Box 3)